跑
Run.
顺便说下我是博士 你叫什么
I'm The Doctor, by the way.What's your name?
洛斯
Rose.
幸会 洛斯 逃命去吧
Nice to meet you, Rose. Run for your life.
它会跟上来的
It's gonna follow us!
连成吉思汗的铁骑都闯不进这扇门
The hordes of Genghis Khan couldn't get through that door.
相信我 他们真的试过
Believe me, they tried.
你是外星人吗 -是的
Are you alien? - Yes.
你可以和我一起走
You could come with me.
总是会像刚才那么危险吗 -是的
Is it always this dangerous? - Yeah.
好了 洛斯·泰勒 告诉我
Right, then, Rose Tyler, you tell me
你想去哪
where do you wanna go?
过去还是未来 任你选
Backwards or forwards in time? It's your choice.
想选哪个
What's it gonna be?
未来
Forwards.
多久以后 -一百年以后
How far? - One hundred years.
到了
There you go.
走出这扇门 就是22世纪
Step outside those doors, it's the 22nd century.
你开玩笑吧
You're kidding.
不过那里很无聊的 想不想走得更远
That's a bit boring, though. Do'you wanna go further?
我没意见
Fine by me.
一万年之后的未来
Ten thousands years in the future.
走出去 就是12005年新罗马帝国
Step outside, it's the year 12005. The new Roman Empire.
你觉得自己特别牛
You think you're so impressive.
我本来就牛 -想得美
I am so impressive. - You wish!
好啊 这可是你自找的
Right, then. You asked for it.
我知道我们该去哪了
I know exactly where to go.
抓稳
Hold on!
我们到哪了
Where are we?
外面是什么
What's out there?
你们人类啊 你们总在想象灭亡
You lot... you spend all your time thinking about dying.
想象你们会被鸡蛋污染或者疯牛病杀死
Like you're gonna get killed by eggs or beef
会被全球变暖或者小行星毁灭掉
or global warming or asteroids.
可你们从来没花时间想过一种可能
But you never take time to imagine the impossible,
你们可能会生存下来
that maybe you survive.
这是5.5/Apple/26年
This is the year 5.5/Apple/26.
五十亿年后的未来
Five billion years in your future.
而就在今天
And this is the day...
等一下
Hold on...
今天就是太阳膨胀的日子
This is the day the sun expands.
欢迎来到世界末日
Welcome to the end of the world.
神秘博士第一季第二集
世界末日
飞船五号和六号正在进港
Shuttles five and six now docking.
请各位来宾注意
Guests are reminded
一号平台禁止使用武器
that Platform One forbids the use of weapons,
禁止瞬间传输和宗教仪式
teleportation and religion.
地球定于十五点三十九分灭亡
Earth-death is scheduled for 15:39,
随后将在曼彻斯特厅举行酒会
followed by drinks in the Manchester Suite.
刚才所说的"来宾"是指人吗
So when it says "guests", does that mean people?
取决于你说的人是什么意思
Depends what you mean by people.
我说的就是人啊 你什么意思
I mean people. What do you mean?
外星人
Aliens.
他们在这艘太空飞船上干什么
What are they doing onboard this spaceship?
它是干什么的
What's it all for?
这并不是一艘太空飞船
It's not really a spaceship.
这更像是一个观景台
It's more like an observation deck.
上流人士们齐聚一堂观赏这颗行星燃烧
The great and the good are gathering to watch the planet burn.
为了什么
What for?
取乐
Fun.
对了 我所说的"上流人士"
Mind you, when I say "the great and the good"
指的就是有钱人
What I mean is the rich.
但 等等 以前《少儿新闻特辑》上播过
But, hold on, they did this once on Newsround Extra,
太阳膨胀
the sun expanding,
需要几百年 -几百万年
that takes hundreds of years. - Millions.
但是这颗行星现在是国家基金会的资产
But the planet's now the property of the National Trust.
他们一直在保护它
They've been keeping it preserved.
看见下面那些了吗
See down there?
重力卫星挡住了太阳
Gravity satellites holding back the sun.
地球看起来和以前一模一样
The planet looks the same as ever.
我还以为大陆板块会漂移什么的
I thought the continents shifted and things.
它们漂移过了 基金会又把它们挪回去了
They did. The Trust shifted them back.
这是经典版地球样貌
That's a Classic Earth.
但现在钱用光了 就要顺从自然规律了
But now the money's run out, nature takes over.
它还有多长时间
How long's it got?
大约半个小时 然后这颗星球就要被烤焦了
About half an hour. Then the planet gets roasted.
所以我们才来这里吗
Is that why we're here?
我是说 这不就是你干的事情吗
I mean, is that what you do?
在最后一刻挺身而出 拯救地球
Jump in at the last minute and save the Earth?
我没打算救它 它的大限到了
I'm not saving it. Time's up.
但是上面的人怎么办
But what about the people?
上面是空的 他们都走了 都离开了
It's empty. They've all gone. All left.
所以只剩下我了 -你们是什么人
Just me, then. - Who the hell are you?
你真友善 谢谢
Oh, that's nice. Thanks.
你们是怎么进来的
But how did you get in?
这里可是顶级接待区
This is a maximum hospitality zone,
来宾们都已经下船了
the guests have disembarked.
他们马上就会到
They're on their way! Any second now...
不 我就是 我就是来宾之一
No, that's me, I'm a guest.
看 我有请柬
Look, I've got an invitation.
看到了吗 没问题的 "博士及一位同伴"
Look. Now you see? It's fine. "The Doctor plus one".
我是博士 这是洛斯·泰勒
I'm the Doctor, this is Rose Tyler,
她是我的同伴 没问题了吧
she's my plus one. Is that all right?
当然
Well, obviously.
非常抱歉
Apologies, et cetera.
既然你们已经到了 我们最好开始吧
If you're on board, we'd better start.
祝您们愉快
Enjoy.
这张纸有一点心灵感应能力
The paper's slightly psychic.
它能显示出我想让他们看到的文字
It shows whatever I want them to see.
省了不少时间
Saves a lot of time.
他是蓝色的
He's blue.
对啊 -好吧
Yeah, - OK.
已经到场的有博士与洛斯·泰勒
We have in attendance the Doctor and Rose Tyler.
谢谢 所有工作人员就位
Thank you. All staff to their positions!
快点 谢谢 尽快 快 快
Hurry now! Thank you! Quick as we can, come along, come along!
现在请允许我介绍下一位尊敬的嘉宾
And now, might I introduce the next honoured guest.
气林族代表
Representing the Forest of Cheam
有请树人们
we have trees,
洁贝 鲁特和卡法
namely Jabe, Lute and Coffa.
下面是互换和平礼物仪式
There will be an exchange of gifts representing peace.
请绕场一周 谢谢
If you could keep the room circulating, thank you...
下一位 来自玖珂律师团
Next, from the solicitors Jolco & Jolco,
有请宝虹星的默克斯
we have the Moxx of Balhoon.
接下来 来自赛文家族财团
And next, from Financial Family Seven,
有请米姆复制党徒
we have the Adherents of the Repeated Meme.
发明亚滑航行系统的
The inventors of Hyposlip Travel Systems,
霍普·派林兄弟
the brothers Hop Pyleen!
"火花塞"卡尔…派库夫妇…
Cal "Sparkplug"... Mr and Mrs Pacoon...
光合城邦大使
The ambassadors from the City-State of Binding Light...
请允许我奉上和平之礼
A gift of peace.
我为您呈上从我祖父身上切下的一根树枝
I bring you a cutting of my grandfather.
谢谢 对了 礼物…
Thank you, yes... gifts, um...
对了 我回赠你…
Ahem! I give you in return...
来自我肺部的空气
air from my lungs.
多么…亲密的礼物
How... intimate.
我这儿还多得是
There's more where that came from.
我猜也是
I bet there is.
我们来自银色荒原的朋友
Our friend from the Silver Devastation,
本次活动的主要赞助商 有请…
the sponsor of the main event, please welcome...
伯欧之脸
The Face of Boe.
宝虹星的默克斯
The Moxx of Balhoon.
为庆祝这一历史性事件
My felicitations upon this historical happenstance.
我献上我的口水作为礼物
I bring the gift of bodily salivas.
非常感谢
Thank you very much.
米姆复制党徒
Ah, the Adherents of the Repeated Meme!
我为你们呈上来自我肺部的空气
I bring you air from my lungs.
一件和平礼物 以示善意
A gift of peace. In all good faith.
最后也是最尊贵的一位 我们的特别来宾
And last but not least, our very special guest.
女士们先生们 树人以及多态生物们
Ladies and gentlemen and trees and multiforms,
想到脚下的地球
consider the Earth, below.
为纪念这个即将逝去的世界
In memory of this dying world,
让我们有请
we call for...
最后一位人类
the Last Human.
卡桑德拉·奥布莱恩·Δ17 女士
The Lady Cassandra O'Brien Dot Delta Seventeen.
别这么看人家嘛
Oh, now don't stare!
我知道 我知道 很惊人 对吗
I know, I know - it's shocking, isn't it?
我完全摘除了下巴
I've had my chin completely taken away,
看看这变化 看我现在多苗条
and look at the difference, look how thin I am!
纤薄优雅
Thin and dainty!
我可不像已经两千多岁的样子
I don't look a day over 2, 000.
给我保湿 给我保湿
Moisturize me. Moisturize me.
是的
Truly,
我是最后一位人类 我父亲是德克萨斯人
I am the Last Human. My father was a Texan,
我母亲来自北极沙漠
my mother was from the Arctic Desert.
他们都在地球出生
They were born on the Earth,
也是最后两个埋葬在这片土地上的人
and they were the last to be buried in its soil.
我来这里缅怀他们
I have come to honour them...
并与他们道别
And say goodbye.
不能哭 不能哭
Oh, no tears, no tears...
对不起
I'm sorry.
但请观赏
But behold!
我带来的礼物
I bring gifts!
来自地球的
From Earth itself,
世上仅存的最后一颗鸵鸟蛋
the last remaining ostrich egg.
传说它有十五米长的巨大翅膀
Legend says it had a wing-span of 50 feet
还能从鼻孔中喷火
and blew fire from its nostrils.
我是不是把它和我的第三任丈夫搞混了
Or was that my THIRD husband?
不 不能笑
Oh, no, oh, don't laugh,
会长皱纹的 不要笑
I'll get laughter-lines. No, stop!
这里 还有另一件稀世珍宝
And here! Another rarity.
据文献记载 这叫做iPod
According to the archives, this was called an iPod,
它存有人类最伟大的作曲家所作的古典乐
it stores classical music from humanity's greatest composers.
播放
Play on!
现在开始上茶点
The refreshments will now be served.
距地球灭亡还有三十分钟
Earth-death in 30 minutes.
博士
Doctor.
谢谢
Thank you.
和平的礼物 满怀善意
A gift of peace. In all good faith.
不 您太客气了 我只是个乘务员
Er, no, you're very kind, but I'm just the steward.
和平的礼物 满怀善意
A gift of peace. In all good faith.
那好吧 谢谢
Oh... yes. Thank you.
收下了
Of course.
鉴别物种
Identify species.
请鉴别物种
Please identify species.
别闹了 快鉴别他的种族 他是哪来的
Now stop it! Identify his race. Where's he from?
这不可能
It's impossible.
对不起 我能到这里来吗
Sorry, am I allowed to be in here?
您得先授予我们谈话的权利
You have to give us permission to talk.
你获得许可了
Y-you have permission.
谢谢
Thank you.
不 您没有妨碍我工作
And, no, you're not in the way.
乘客可以到任何地方
Guests are allowed anywhere.
你叫什么名字
What's your name?
拉法罗
Raffalo.
是的 小姐
Yes, Miss.
我不会待太久的 只是来做个维修
I... I won't be long I've just got to carry out some maintenance.
伯欧之脸的套房里有点小故障
There's a tiny little glitch in the Face of Boe's suite.
估计有什么东西把系统堵住了
There must be something blocking the system.
他的房间里没有热水
He's not getting any hot water.
那你就是个水管工了
So... you're a plumber?
是的 小姐
That's right Miss.
现在还有水管工吗
They still have plumbers?
希望如此 不然我就要失业了
I hope so, else I'm out of a job!
你是哪里人 -克拉斯帕里安
Where are you from? - Crespallion.
那是个星球吗
That's a planet, is it?
不 克拉斯帕里安是附属于56号凸面的
No, Crespallion's part of the Jaggit Brocade
猩红节点的加杰特·布罗凯德行星群的一部分
affiliated to the Scarlet Junction. Convex 56.
您是哪里人 小姐
And where are you from, Miss?
如果您不介意我问的话 -没关系
If you don't mind my asking? - No, not at all...
我也不知道
Um, I don't know.
我从一个很远的地方来
A long way away.
我只是跟一个人搭了趟顺风车
I just sort of hitched a lift with this man...
我甚至都没想过会这样
I didn't even think about it.
甚至不知道他是谁
Don't even know who he is.
他根本就是个陌生人
He's a complete stranger.
总之 不耽误你工作了 祝你好运
Anyway, um, don't let me keep you. Good luck with it!
谢谢 小姐 还有…
Thank you, Miss. And, er...
谢谢您给我许可
thank you for the permission.
很少有人会这么体贴
Not many people are that considerate.
待会见
OK... see you later.
现在
Now, then.
控制台 我在第19个接口
Control, I'm at junction 19.
我觉得问题就出在这里
I think the problem's coming from in here.
我准备进去仔细检查一下
I'll go inside and have a look.
什么东西 有东西在里面吗
What's that? Is there something in there?
你是谁呀
Ooh, who are you, then?
等等
Hold on!
如果你是个更新 我只要给你登记一下
If you're an upgrade, I just need to register you,
没别的了 快回来
that's all. Oh, come back.
你回来了啊
Ah, there you are.
我只要登记一下你的编号
Now, I just need to register your ident.
来了两个啊 带了个小伙伴吗
Aw, there's two of ya! Got yourself a little mate?
我想我还是向控制台汇报一下吧
I think I'd better report this to control.
你们一共有几个
How many of you are there?
你们是什么东西
What are you?
不要
Oh, no!
不 不
No! No!
怎么回事
What's that?
我怎么会知道
Well, how should I know?
请15号私人画廊里蓝色盒子的主人
Would the owner of the blue box in Private Gallery 15
马上到乘务员办公室报到
please report to the steward's office immediately.
乘客请注意
Guests are reminded that
根据和平条约5.4章C16条的内容
the use of teleportation devices is strictly forbidden
严禁使用任何空间传送装置 谢谢合作
under peace treaty 5.4/Cup/16. Thank you.
距地球灭亡还有二十五分钟
Earth-death in 25 minutes.
谢谢
Oh, thanks.
你好
Hello.
我叫洛斯
My name's Rose.
也是某种植物
That's a... sort of plant.
咱俩说不定是亲戚呢
We might be related.
我竟然在跟树枝说话
I'm talking to a twig.
喂 小心点 妥善保管 别刮花了
Oi now, careful with that, park it properly. No scratches.
洛斯 你在里面吗
Rose, are you in there?
你觉得怎么样 -好极了
What d'you think, then? - Great, yeah. Fine.
一旦接受了通灵纸片的设定
Once you get past the slightly psychic paper.
他们看上去太有外星范儿了
They're just so alien!
这些外星人太有外星范儿了
The aliens are so alien.
看着就像外星人
You look at 'em... and they're alien.
还好我没把你带到蛮荒之地去
Good thing I didn't take you to the deep South
你是从哪里来的
Where are you from?
各种地方
All over the place.
他们都讲英语 -只是你听到的是英语而已
They all speak English. - No, you just hear English.
这是塔迪斯的能力 心灵感应场
It's a gift of the TARDIS. Telepathic field,
它会在你脑中将这些语言都翻译成英语
gets inside your brain, translates.
它在我脑子里吗
It's inside my brain?
不是坏事 -你的机器进到了我脑子里
Well, in a good way. - Your machine gets inside my head?
不仅进去了 还在影响着我的头脑
It gets inside and it changes my mind,
你都没问我一声
and you didn't even ask?
我没有考虑到这点
I didn't think about it like that.
不 你忙着想着
No, you were too busy
怎么挖苦遥远的蛮荒之地了
thinking up cheap shots about the Deep South!
那你是谁呢 博士
Who are you, then, Doctor?
你又是什么呢
What're you called?
你是哪种外星人 -我只是博士
What sort of alien are you? - I'm just the Doctor.
哪个星球来的
From what planet?
我说了你也不知道 -你从哪里来的
It's not as if you'd know it where it is. - Where are you from?
这有关系吗
What's it matter?
告诉我你是谁 -我就是我
Tell me who you are! - This is who I am,
此时此刻 行了吗
right here, right now, all right?
你只要关心此时此刻就好了
All that counts is here and now.
这就是我 -是啊 我也在这里
And this is me. - Yes, and I'm here too,
因为是你把我带过来的 所以告诉我
coz you brought me here. So just tell me!
距地球灭亡还有二十分钟
Earth-death in 20 minutes.
好吧
All right.
我好友席琳说过
As my mate Shireen says,
别跟你的司机吵架
don't argue with the designated driver.
这时候我也叫不到什么计程车
Can't exactly call for a taxi.
无信号
No signal.
我们超出服务区范围了 超了一点点吧
We're out of range. Just a bit.
我告诉你
Tell you what.
只要设置欺骗式干扰器
With a little bit of Jiggery-Pokery...
这是技术术语吗 欺骗式干扰器
Is that a technical term, Jiggery-Pokery
是啊 我先想到欺骗式干扰器的 你呢
Yes, I came first in Jiggery-Pokery. What about you?
不 想不出什么更厉害的名字
No, failed hullabaloo.
拿去吧
There you go.
联系人 妈妈
你好
Hello?
妈妈 -怎么了
Mum? - Oh, what is it?
怎么了 又出什么事了
What's wrong, what have I done now?
这件红衣服都褪色了
Ooh, this red top's falling to bits!
你得把钱退回来
You should get your money back.
说吧 肯定出什么事了
Go on, there must be something.
你从来不会大白天的打电话给我
You never phone in the middle of the day...
有什么好笑的
What's so funny?
没什么 那你没事吧 -能有什么事啊
Nothing. You all right, though? - Yeah, why wouldn't I be?
今天是什么时候
What day is it?
星期三 你又醉了一晚上吗
Wednesday all day. You got a hangover?
对了 你去帮我买个一块钱的彩票
Ooh, I tell you what, put a quid in that lottery syndicate.
我过会把钱还给你 -好的 我
I'll pay you back later. - Yeah, um, I...
我打电话来是想说 我可能要晚点回家
I was just calling cos... I might be late home.
出什么事了吗 -不 我很好
Is there something wrong? - No, I'm fine.
好得不得了
Top of the world!
是不是很神奇 想看看这通电话的账单吗
Think that's amazing, you wanna see the bill?
那是50亿年前
That was five billion years ago.
所以
So...
她现在已经死了
She's dead now.
50亿年以后 我妈妈早就死了
Five billion years later, my mum's dead.
你可真有意思
Bundle of laughs, you are.
不应该发生这种震荡的
That's not supposed to happen.
怎么回事 我这边显示一切正常
Well, what was it? I'm just getting green lights at this end.
各位尊贵的客人们请放心
Honoured guests may be reassured that
重力阱可能会引起轻微的震荡 谢谢
gravity pockets may cause slight turbulence. Thanking you...
这整个地方都在晃 我感觉到了
The whole place shook! I felt it!
我负责一 三 六及十五号平台事务以来
I've hosted all sorts of events on platforms 1,
从没感觉到过一丁点震动
3, 6 and 15 and never felt the slightest tremor.
我警告你 要是客人来投诉的话…
I warn you, if this lot decide to sue...!
我得去检查一下基础设备
I'm gonna scan the infrastructure.
怎么回事
What's that?
控制台 我不是危言耸听
Control, I don't want to worry you
但是我接受到了一些数据
but I'm picking up readings...
我不知道 他们很小 扫描显示是金属制品
I have no idea! They're small. The scan says they're metal...
我不知道他们长什么样
I don't know what they look like!
不过我觉得他们可能长得像这样
Although I imagine they might look rather like that.
你不在宾客名单上
You're not on the guest list.
你是怎么上船的
How did you get on board?
不 -阳光过滤器关闭
No! - Sun filter deactivated.
不
No!
阳光过滤器关闭中
Sun filter descending.
不 开启阳光过滤器
No! Sun filter up!
不不不
No, no, no!
控制台请回复 -阳光过滤器关闭中
Control! Respond! - Sun filter descending.
开启阳光过滤器
Sun filter up!
阳光过滤器关闭中
Sunfilter descending...
毫无疑问 这已经是“恶狼情形”了
Indubitably, this is the bad-wolf scenario.
我发现了未知的多元宇宙的松弛性…
I find the inherent laxity of the unknown multiverse...
那不是重力阱造成的 我了解重力阱
That wasn't a gravity pocket, I know gravity pockets,
不是这种的感觉 你怎么看 洁贝
and they don't feel like that... What do you think, Jabe?
听听引擎
Listen to the engines.
频率快到三十赫兹了 是不是出了问题
They've pitched up about 30 hertz. Is that dodgy or what?!
那是金属的声音 我根本听不懂
It's the sound of metal - it doesn't make any sense to me.
引擎室在哪里
Where's the engine room?
我不知道
I don't know.
不过维修管道就在客舱的后面
But the maintenance duct is just behind our guest suite.
我可以带你…和你夫人去看
I could show you. And... your wife.
她不是我夫人
Oh, she's not my wife.
伴侣 -不是
Partner? - No.
情妇
Concubine?
不是
Nope.
妓女
Prostitute?
不论我是谁
Whatever I am,
都被当成隐形人了 对吗
it must be invisible. Do you mind?!
要不你们两个去…授粉吧
Tell you what, you two go... pollinate.
我找家人叙叙旧
I'll catch up with family.
和迈克尔·杰克逊聊两句
Quick word with Michael Jackson.
别打起来
Don't start a fight.
任你差遣
I'm all yours.
午夜前给我乖乖回家
And I want you home by midnight.
距地球灭亡还有十五分钟
Earth-death in 15 minutes.
谁负责一号平台 有没有舰长什么的
Who's in charge of Platform One? Has it got a captain or what?
只有管理员和工作人员
There's just the steward and staff.
剩下都是由金属脑袋控制的
All the rest is controlled by the metalmind.
你是说计算机吗
You mean the computer?
那谁控制它呢 -公司
Well, who controls that? - The Corporation.
他们让一号平台在各个艺术活动间移动
They move Platform One from one artistic event to another.
没有公司的人在船上吗
There's no-one from the corporation on board?
没必要 这个地方全自动化了
They're not needed. This facility is purely automatic.
最好的阿尔法级飞船
It's the height of the Alpha Class.
从不出错 -永不沉没
Nothing can go wrong. - Unsinkable.
随你怎么说 用航海术语比喻很恰当
If you like. The nautical metaphor is appropriate.
完全同意
You're telling me!
我曾登上另一艘号称永不沉没的船
I was on board another ship once and they said that was unsinkable.
结果撞上了冰山 冻死我了
I ended up clinging to an iceberg. Wasn't half cold.
你是说 如果我们出了麻烦
So what you're saying is if we get in trouble,
没人能来帮我们
there's no-one to help us out.
恐怕是没有 -妙极了
I'm afraid not. - Fantastic!
我不明白
I don't understand.
这怎么能说是妙极了
In what way is that fantastic?
很快太阳就会膨胀成红巨星
Soon the sun will blossom into a red giant
我的家园也将随之逝去
and my home will die.
我还是个小男孩时就生活在那里
That's where I used to live, when I was a little boy.
就在下面
Down there.
妈妈和爸爸有座房子
Mummy and Daddy had a house
建在旧金山峡谷里
built into the side of the Los Angeles Crevasse.
多么快乐的时光
Ah, I'd have such fun.
其他人呢 人类去哪里了
What happened to everyone else? The human race, where did it go?
有人说人类已经遍布宇宙繁星
They say mankind has touched every star in the sky.
所以你不是最后一个人类
So you're not the last human.
我是最后一个纯种人类
I am the Last Pure Human.
其他人成了 混血
The others... mingled.
他们自称为新人类
Oh, they call themselves New Humans
原人类 数字人类 甚至泛人类
and Protohumans and Digihumans - even Human-ish
知道我怎么称呼他们吗
but d'you know what I call them?
杂种
Mongrels.
说得对 而你却保持不变
Right. And you stayed behind.
我保持血统纯正
I kept myself pure.
你做了多少次整容手术
How many operations have you had?
708次 下周第709次
708. Next week, it's 709.
我要漂白血液
I'm having my blood bleached.
所以你才来和我聊天 对吗
Is that why you wanted a word?
你可以更平一点 洛斯
You could be flatter, Rose.
你的下巴有点凸出
You've got a little bit of a... chin poking out.
先杀了我吧 -一点都不痛 真的
I'd rather die. - Honestly, it doesn't hurt.
说真的 你宁愿去死
I mean it. I would rather die.
死了也比你这样活着好 毒舌蹦床
It's better to die than to live like you, a bitchy trampoline.
你懂什么
Oh, well, what do YOU know?
我就出生在这颗星球上
I was born on that planet.
我妈妈是 我爸爸也是 所以我
And so was my mum, and so was my dad, and that makes me,
才是这个房间里最后一个人类
officially, the last human being in this room.
你不是人类
Cos you're not human.
你身上人类的部分都被割掉拆光碾平了
You've had it all nipped and tucked and flattened
什么都不剩
till there's nothing left.
人的那部分都被扔掉了
Anything human got chucked in the bin.
你就剩一张皮 卡桑德拉 涂口红的皮
You're just skin, Cassandra, lipstick and skin.
很高兴和你聊天
Nice talking.
告诉我 洁贝
So, tell me, Jabe,
像你这样一棵树到这里来做什么
what's a tree like you doing in a place like this?
向地球表达敬意 -得了吧
Respect for the Earth. - Oh, come on,
平台上哪个人不是家资巨富
everyone on this Platform's worth zillions.
也许还因为
Well. Perhaps it's a case
这是一个需要露面的场合
of having to be seen at the right occasions.
防止你的股票下跌 我了解你这种人
In case your share prices drop? I know you lot,
你们有巨大的森林 四处生根
you've got massive forests, roots everywhere.
而土地又总能赚钱
And there's always money in land.
虽说如此 我们确实把地球看作家园
All the same, we respect the Earth as family.
很多种族从这里演化而来
So many species evolved from that planet.
人类只是其中之一
Mankind is only one.
我属于另一种 我的祖先就是从
I'm another. My ancestors were transplanted
下面这颗星球上移植而来的
from the planet down below,
我是热带雨林的直系后代
and I'm a direct descendant of the tropical rainforest.
不好意思
Excuse me.
你的祖先呢 博士
And what about your ancestry, Doctor?
也许你也有故事要讲
Perhaps you could tell a story or two.
也许一个人喜欢自找麻烦只是因为
Perhaps a man only enjoys trouble unless
他别无所有
there's nothing else left...?
之前我扫描了你
I scanned you earlier.
金属机器一开始无法辨别出你的种族
The metalmachine had trouble identifying your species.
它拒绝承认你的存在
It refused to admit your existence.
即使在它说出了你的种族之后
And even when it named you,
我还是无法相信
I wouldn't believe it.
不过它是对的
But it was right.
我知道你来自哪里
I know where you're from!
恕我冒昧 但是
Forgive me for intruding, but...
你的存在本身就是奇迹
it's remarkable that you even exist.
我只想说
I just want to say...
我十分抱歉
how sorry I am.
只有我觉得有点冷吗
Is it me, or is it a bit nippy?
不过效果很好 很不错的一种制冷系统
Fair do's though - that's a great bit of air-conditioning.
老式而有效
Sort of nice and old-fashioned.
我猜他们称之为复古
Bet they call it retro.
找到了
Gotcha.
那是什么鬼东西 -也是复古的一部分吗
What the hell's that? - Is it part of the "retro"?
我不这么想 等等
I don't think so, hold on.
藤法不错 -谢谢
Hey, nice liana. - Thank you.
本不应该在外人面前用的
Not supposed to show them in public.
别担心 我不会告诉任何人
Don't worry, I won't tell anybody.
谁把宠物带上了船
Now then, who's been bringing their pets on board?
它有什么用
What does it do?
搞破坏 -距地球灭亡还有十分钟
Sabotage... - Earth-death in ten minutes...
温度马上就会飙升了
And the temperature's about to rocket.
快走 -距地球灭亡还有十分钟
Come on. - Earth death in ten minutes.
这颗星球末日将至
The planet's end!
让我们聚拢一处
Come gather, come gather!
向这个文明的摇篮道别
Bid farewell to the cradle of civilisation.
让我们用一首古老的民谣为它哀悼
Let us mourn her with a traditional ballad.
好了 别着急 都退后
All right, hold on, get back.
阳光过滤器开启 阳光过滤器开启
Sunfilter rising. Sunfilter rising.
管理员在里面吗 -你能闻到他
Is the Steward in there? - You can smell him.
等等 还有一个阳光过滤器正在关闭
Hold on. There's another sunfilter programmed to descend.
阳光过滤器关闭中
Sunfilter descending.
Sunfilter descending...
阳光过滤器关闭中
让我出去 -阳光过滤器关闭中
Let me out! Let me out! - Sunfilter descending...
让我出去 让我出去
Let me out! Let me out!
阳光过滤器关闭中
Sunfilter descending.
Sunfilter descending...
有人在里面吗
Anyone in there?
让我出去 -一猜就是你
Let me out! - Oh, well, it would be you.
开门
Open the door!
稍等一下
Hold on two ticks...
阳光过滤器关闭中
Sunfilter descending.
阳光过滤器开启
Sunfilter rising. Sunfilter rising.
阳光过滤器关闭中
Sunfilter descending.
怕什么来什么 计算机变聪明了
Just what we need - the computer's getting clever.
别开玩笑了
Stop mucking about!
我没在开玩笑 它在反抗
I'm not mucking about! It's fighting back.
阳光过滤器关闭中 -开门
Sunfilter descending. - Open the door!
我知道
I know!
阳光过滤器关闭中 -锁熔化了
Sunfilter descending. - The lock's melted!
阳光过滤器关闭中
Sunfilter descending.
阳光过滤器开启
Sunfilter rising. Sunfilter rising...
全卡在一块儿了
The whole thing's jammed.
我打不开门 待在里面 不要动
I can't open the door. Stay there, don't move.
我又能去哪 伊普斯维奇吗
Where am I gonna go - Ipswich.
距地球灭亡还有五分钟
Earth-death in five minutes.
金属机器确定了
The metalmachine confirms.
蜘蛛机器已经遍布整个一号平台
The spider devices have infiltrated the whole of Platform One.
怎么可能
How's that possible?
我们的私人房间都有密码墙保护
Our private rooms are protected by a codewall.
给我保湿 给我保湿
Moisturize me. Moisturize me.
叫管理员来 -恐怕管理员已经去世了
Summon the Steward! - I'm afraid the Steward is dead.
谁杀了他
Who killed him?
整个行程都是伯欧之脸资助的
This whole event was sponsored by the Face of Boe.
他邀请了我们 去问伯欧之脸
He invited us. Talk to the Face, talk to the Face!
想找出来很简单
Easy way of finding out.
有人把他们的小宠物带上了船
Someone brought their little pet on board.
让他找主人去
Let's send him back to master.
米姆复制党徒 我要控诉
The Adherents of the Repeated Meme! J'accuse!
很好 而且确实挺明确的 但是
That's all very well, and really kind of obvious but,
如果你仔细想一下…
if you stop and think about it...
米姆复制充其量只是一种想法
A repeated meme is just an idea.
他们也是 只是想法驱动而已
And that's all they are, an idea.
远程操控的机器人
Remote-control 'droids.
真正破坏者的完美掩护
Nice little cover for the real troublemaker.
走吧 小伙子 回家去
Go on, Jimbo. Go home.
我猜你小时候一定是那种没人喜欢的书呆子
I bet you were the school swot and never got kissed.
抄家伙
At arms!
你想干什么 给我保湿吗
What you gonna do, moisturise me?
用酸液
With acid.
不过反正你也活不长了
Oh, you're too late, anyway.
我的小蜘蛛们已经控制了平台主机
My spiders have control of the mainframe.
你们都把它们做为礼物
Oh, you all carried them as gifts,
不费吹灰之力 通过了每一层密码墙
tax-free, past every codewall.
我可不只有张表皮
I'm not just a pretty face.
你自己也在船上 要毁掉它简直太愚蠢了
Sabotaging a ship while you're inside it, how stupid's that?
我本打算营造一起人质事件
I'd hoped to manufacture a hostage situation.
我也是人质之一
With myself as one of the victims,
这样就能收到巨额赔偿
the compensation would have been enormous.
五十亿年了 大家在乎的还是钱
Five billion years, and it still comes down to money.
你以为保持美貌很便宜吗
D'you think it's cheap, looking like this?
平整自己很烧钱的
Flatness costs a fortune!
我才是最后的人类 博士
I am the Last Human, Doctor.
是我 而不是你那个呆头姑娘
Me, not that freaky little kid of yours.
逮捕她 这个异教徒
Arrest her! The infidel!
闭嘴 丑妖怪 还好我留了一手
Oh, shut it, Pixie! I've still got my final option.
距地球灭亡还有三分钟
Earth-death in three minutes,
距地球灭亡还有三分钟 -时候到了
earth-death in three minutes... - And here it comes.
你们这些人死了也一样管用
You're just as useful dead, all of you.
我买了你们的竞争公司的股票
I have shares in your rival companies.
你们一死他们的股价会翻上三番
They'll triple in price as soon as you're dead.
我的小蜘蛛们已经准备好摧毁安全系统
My spiders are primed and ready to destroy the safety systems.
那首古老的地球歌怎么唱来着
How did that old Earth song go?
"燃烧吧 宝贝 燃烧"
"Burn baby, burn."
那你会跟我们一起死
Then you'll burn with us!
真不好意思
Oh, I'm so sorry!
我知道这里严禁使用瞬间移动 但是
I know the use of teleportation is strictly forbidden, but...
我就是不爱乖乖听话
I'm such a naughty thing.
蜘蛛们 行动
Spiders, activate!
保护力场失效了 地球马上就会爆炸
Force-fields gone, with the planet about to explode...
至少你们会死得很快
At least it'll be quick.
就像我的第五任丈夫那样
Just like my fifth husband...
真是不好意思 再见了 亲爱的各位
Oops! Oh, shame on me! Bye bye, darlings.
安全系统失效
Safety systems failing...
永别了 我亲爱的
Bye-bye, my darlings!
热度升高
Heat levels rising...
重启电脑 -只有管理员知道怎么做
Reset the computer! - Only the Steward would know how.
不对 我们可以手动操作
No, we can do it by hand.
一定有"系统重启"开关 洁贝 我们走
There must be a "system restore" switch. Jabe, come on.
各位 保持冷静
You lot, just chill.
距地球灭亡还有两分钟
Earth-death in two minutes.
Earthdeath in two minutes.
热度超过临界值
Heat levels critical,
heat levels critical.
猜猜看开关在哪
Oh, and guess where the switch is.
热度升高 热度升高
Heat levels rising. Heat levels rising.
外部温度五千度
External temperature 5, 000 degrees.
你不能那么做 高温会排到这里的
You can't, the heat's gonna vent through this place.
我知道 -洁贝
I know. - Jabe!
你是木头做的
You're made of wood.
那就别再浪费时间了 时间领主
Then stop wasting time - Time Lord.
热度升高
Heat levels rising...
Heat levels rising.
我们要死了 -高温危险
We're going to die! - Heat levels hazardous...
护盾失效
Shields malfunction...
Shields malfunction.
护盾失效
热度超过临界值
Heat levels critical...
Heat levels critical.
热度升高中
Heat levels rising.
地球爆炸倒计时
Planet explodes in...
十
ten,
九
nine...
八
eight...
七
seven...
六
six...
五
five...
四
four...
升起护盾
Raise shields!
一
One.
外层玻璃已修复
Exoglass repair. Exoglass repair...
你没事吧 -我没事
You all right? - Yeah, I'm fine.
我脑中充满想法 满脑都是
I'm full of ideas. I'm bristling with 'em!
第一个想法
Idea number one.
在五千度下瞬间传送需要信号馈入装置
Teleportation through 5,000 degrees needs some kind of feed.
第二个想法 这个装置一定藏在附近
Idea number two. This feed must be hidden nearby.
第三个想法
Idea number three.
如果你像我一样聪明
If you're as clever as me,
那么瞬间移动信号可以被逆转
then a teleportation-feed can be reversed.
你真应该看看
Oh, you should've seen
那群外星人小脸上的表情
their little alien faces...
最后的人类
The last human.
看来 你通过我的小测试了 做得好
So. You passed my little test. Bravo!
这让你有资格加入…人类俱乐部
This makes you eligible to join, um, the... the Human Club.
有人死了 卡桑德拉 是你杀了他们
People have died, Cassandra. You murdered them.
那得取决你怎么定义人
It depends on your definition of people.
而这个技术细节
And that's enough of a technicality
足够你的律师纠结几个世纪了
to keep your lawyers dizzy for centuries.
有本事就去告我吧 博士
Take me to court then, Doctor,
然后你就看我在庭上微笑 哭泣
and watch me smile and cry...
还有颤抖 -还会咯吱响
and flutter. - And creak?
什么 -咯吱响 你在响
And what? - Creak. You're creaking.
你说什么
What?
我…我快干死了
Agh! I-I'm drying out!
天呐 给我保湿 给我保湿
Oh, sweet heavens! Moisturise me, moisturise me!
我的医生们哪去了 我可爱的小伙子们呢
Where are my surgeons, my lovely boys?
这里太热了 -是你升高的温度
It's too hot! - YOU raised the temperature.
可怜可怜我吧
Have pity!
给我保湿
Moisturise me!
博士
Oh, Doctor!
博士 我愿意做任何事 -帮帮她
Oh, Doctor, I'll do anything...! - Help her.
所有东西都有寿命时限 万物终有一死
Everything has its time. And everything dies.
我…还…太年轻
I'm... too... young...!
飞船四号 六号离港中
Shuttles four and six departing.
本平台将关闭维修
This unit now closing down for maintenance.
地球末日
The end of the Earth.
它毁灭了
It's gone.
我们都忙着救自己 没人注意它的消逝
We were too busy saving ourselves. No one saw it go.
亿万年的时间 亿万年的历史
All those years, all that history,
最终却无人注意
and no-one was even looking.
这太…
It's just...
跟我来
Come with me.
《大问题》杂志
Big Issue!
Big Issue...!
你以为这些都会永远一成不变
You think it'll last forever,
人群 汽车 房子
people and cars and concrete.
但其实不会
But it won't.
有一天 他们都会终结
One day, it's all gone.
包括天空
Even the sky.
我的星球也不在了
My planet's gone.
它毁灭了
It's dead.
像地球一样烧毁了
It burned, like the Earth.
只剩碎石和尘埃
It's just rocks and dust.
它本来还不到时候
Before its time.
怎么回事
What happened?
发生了一场战争 我们输了
There was a war, and we lost.
和谁的战争
A war with who?
那你们的人民呢
What about your people?
我是时间领主
I'm a Time Lord.
我是最后的时间领主
I'm the last of the Time Lords.
他们都死了
They're all gone.
我是唯一的幸存者
I'm the only survivor.
我孤身一人旅行是因为没有别人了
I'm left travelling on my own cos there's no-one else.
你还有我
There's me.
你也看到有多危险了 你想回家吗
You've seen how dangerous it is. D'you wanna go home?
我不知道
I don't know.
我想…
I want...
你闻到薯条味了吗
Can you smell chips?
闻到了
Yeah.
当然闻到了 -我想吃薯条
Yeah! - I want chips.
我也是
Me too.
那好 在我们回那个盒子之前
Right, then. Before you get me back in that box,
先吃薯条 你请客 -没钱
Chips it is. And you can pay. - No money.
你就这么和女孩约会啊
What sort of date are you?
那好吧 小气鬼 我请你吃薯条
Come on, then, tightwad. Chips are on me.
我们离那家店关门只剩下五十亿年了
We've only got five billion years till the shops close.
下集预告
你见识过了未来
Now - you've seen the future,
这回去看看过去吧
so let's have a look at the past.
1860年听起来如何
1860, how does 1860 sound?
1860年怎么了
What happened in 1860?
我不知道 一起去看看
I don't know. Let's find out.
我简直不敢相信她去了
I can't believe she's gone.
不是去了 雷德帕斯先生 睡着了而已
Not gone, Mr Redpath, sir. Merely sleeping.
她又起来活蹦乱跳了 现在不知所踪
She's up and on her feet and out there somewhere.
丢脸啊斯尼德先生
Mr. Sneed for shame,
还要闹几次 简直天理难容啊
how many more times? It's ungodly!
打扰了 狄更斯先生 该您上场了
Excuse me, sir. Mr Dickens, this is your call.
用你的天眼
Use the sight.
赶紧找到老太太 否则你就被开除了
Find the old lady or you're dismissed.
这是什么戏法
What phantasmagoria is this?
这才像话
That's more like it!